"Preventing and Treating Sarcoidosis"
Sarcoidosis is a disease
characterized by granulomas,
which are collections
of immune cells
caused by chronic inflammation
that can form in our lungs,
lymph nodes, on our skin,
and in other parts of our body.
The occurrence of sarcoidosis
varies greatly around the world,
from fairly low levels
in countries like South Korea,
Taiwan, and Japan
to up to a hundred times
higher levels
in Sweden and Canada.
Race also seems to matter,
with Black populations experiencing
much higher rates of disease
and higher rates of death
at younger ages.
It's possible Black people
may be at greater risk
of disease
and disease severity,
but there are
also long-standing
systemic health
and social inequities
that limit access
to quality care.
The routine way
to treat sarcoidosis
is with immune-suppressing
corticosteroid drugs
to manage the inflammation.
Drugs come with their own
limitations, though,
including steroid resistance,
no response to the medications,
and a long list
of potential side effects.
Could nutrition help
in sarcoidosis treatment?
Possibly.
Certain components in food
may have anti-inflammatory
effects in lung diseases,
so, maybe sarcoidosis patients
should be encouraged
to eat antioxidant
and polyphenol-rich diets,
but there have yet to be
interventional trials
to put it to the test.
Are there any steps
we can take
to potentially avoid
this disease?
Its cause is unknown.
Sarcoidosis can cluster
in families,
but maybe that's just because
of a shared household
environment.
Although some gene variants
may increase susceptibility,
genes alone are insufficient
to cause sarcoidosis.
Something is driving
the disease process.
the inflammation.
We may be closer to solving
one part of the mystery
of sarcoidosis.
Recent advances in molecular
and immunological methods
have produced
a more rigorous look
at the drivers of the disease,
indicating that mycobacteria
are likely involved
in at least a subset
of sarcoidosis cases.
Mycobacteria like
Mycobacterium avium
paratuberculosis,
or MAP, M-A-P,
is a zoonotic pathogen,
meaning it can go
from animals to humans.
We previously covered
the potential link between MAP
and other autoimmune conditions,
like type 1 diabetes,
and how dairy products
are a major exposure source
in our diets to MAP.
Viable MAP bacteria
are still being found
in pasteurized milk,
despite efforts to extend
the pasteurization processes
to prevent this.
It's also found in goat milk
and various types
of cheeses:
Swiss, cheddar, sheep,
and goat cheeses,
along with softer cheeses
like mozzarella and burrata.
Unfortunately,
this is a global issue
in countries raising cows
in intensive systems,
with among the highest rates
in the United States,
where 68 to 91 percent
of dairy herds are infected.
In this 2015 review,
two studies looked
for MAP bacteria
and found none
in either sarcoidosis patients
or control subjects.
And two other studies looked
at evidence of MAP exposure
and found between 7
and 17 times the odds
of reacting to MAP,
but neither reached
statistical significance.
What have we learned
since then?
In a natural experiment,
researchers looked at the rates
of sarcoidosis
among those who did or did not
receive the BCG vaccine,
which provides
partial protection
against mycobacteria
like tuberculosis.
And those born during a time
with high
BCG vaccination uptake
had lower rates of sarcoidosis.
But it's not like it was a
randomized controlled experiment,
so it's not clear
if tuberculosis vaccination
could really protect
from MAP-associated
autoimmune diseases,
which also include
Crohn's disease,
Hashimoto's thyroiditis,
MS, rheumatoid arthritis,
and lupus.
The strongest evidence would
come from seeing an effect
from treating someone
with antimycobacterial drugs.
That's how Barry Marshall
got the Nobel prize
for proving that H. pylori
caused stomach inflammation,
by swallowing some,
then curing himself
with antibiotics.
This is the study that excited
the sarcoidosis community.
Cardiac sarcoidosis,
meaning sarcoidosis
of the heart,
resolved with MAP antibiotics.
MAP was first identified
in this patient's blood,
and after more than a year
of a MAP antibiotic regime,
his sarcoidosis appeared
to disappear,
something that was never
even thought possible.
A pilot study in those
with pulmonary sarcoidosis
also found impressive results
with antimycobacterial therapy,
with improvements
in lung function
and quality of life.
When the researchers conducted
a larger trial, however,
there was no significant benefit
for lung function
despite a significant reduction
in mycobacterial
immune responses.
So, where does that leave us?
Mycobacterial avium
paratuberculosis
in the food supply
is a public health issue.
"To reduce human exposure
to MAP
via consumption of dairy
and meat products,
more studies are needed
for estimating"
how much MAP
is in the milk, meat,
and feces of these animals
and how much fecal contamination
is in the milk and meat,
to figure out what we
need to do to kill it.